Guide to the Ralph W. Tyler Papers 1932-1988
University of Chicago Library
Tyler, Ralph W. Papers
1932-1988
46.5 linear feet (90 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Ralph W. Tyler (1902-1994) Professor of Education and university administrator. Contains correspondence, minutes, sample dissertations, examinations, manuscripts of speeches and articles, published works, biographical material, and letters of recommendation. Papers document Tyler's involvement with the United States Department of Agriculture Extension Service workshops, Doane College, the American Council on Education, and the University of Chicago Department of Education and Division of Social Sciences, as well as other organizations.
Information on Use
Access
Series VII contains student evaluative materials that are restricted until 2068. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Ralph W. Tyler was born in Chicago, IL on April 22, 1902, the son of Reverend William A. Tyler. He earned his BA at Doane University in Nebraska and his Master's degree in 1923 at the University of Nebraska. Tyler's Ph.D. was granted by the University of Chicago in 1927. After teaching at the University of Nebraska (1922-1927) and the University of North Carolina (1927-1929), Tyler moved to Ohio State University as Professor of Education and Research Associate of the Bureau of Educational Research (1929-1938).
Tyler specialized in measuring the application of education. Before arriving at the University of Chicago he led "the eight year study" which measured to what degree students absorbed information given to them by their teachers. The study showed that children learned best at their own pace and students best retained information compounded by experience. This program led to national testing for pre-college students.
When Tyler met with the President of the University of Chicago to recommend methods for testing applicants, the thirty five year old professor held a reputation as a progressive educator who smoked cigars constantly and raced cars against trains. Although University of Chicago president Robert Hutchins believed in classical education, in 1938 he risked hiring Tyler as the Chief Examiner and Director of the Board of Examinations, Professor of Education, and Chair of the Department of Education. Tyler accepted and moved to Chicago with his entire testing staff.
Tyler became acting Dean of Social Sciences when Dean Robert Redfield took a leave of absence in 1946. Tyler was officially appointed as dean in 1948. He streamlined the committees between the departments and promoted interdisciplinary studies. Additionally, Tyler participated in University life by contributing to the Great Books Program and to the Chicago Roundtable radio discussions. Additionally, Tyler continuously published the results of his work.
Through the course of his tenure at the University of Chicago his positions included: Chairman, Department of Education, University of Chicago (1938-48); University Examiner, University of Chicago (1938-53); Dean, Division of the Social Sciences, University of Chicago (1948-53); Director, Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Stanford, California (1953-67); Acting President, Social Science Research Council (1971-72); Vice President, Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (1975-78); and President, System Development Foundation (1969-until his death?).
Additionally, Tyler served as the official Director of the Examinations Staff of the U.S. Armed Forces Institute from 1943-1954 during which the military asked him to administer tests to measure the effectiveness of its training programs.
In the 1960's, Tyler worked with his colleagues on the National Assessment of Educational Progress, measuring educational achievements around the United States. Tyler advised six U.S. Presidents and assisted in writing the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965. After leaving the University of Chicago in 1953, Tyler moved to California as the founding director of the Center for the Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, funded by the Ford Foundation (1953-1967). Throughout the 1980's Tyler commuted from California to the University of Massachusetts at Amherst to teach and advise the Coalition for School Improvement.
Tyler's style of testing became common and was known as the "Tyler Rationale". His methods were initially considered unorthodox because he advocated the involvement of teachers and parents at every level of school reform. Tyler believed that the purpose of education was to teach children how to function as citizens. He stated, "Carrying on citizenship is the most important reason for public education…As society keeps moving forward, we need to have more and more education to understand problems that are much more complex than those that were dealt with in 1776."
Tyler's wife, Flora V. Tyler passed away before he did. Ralph Tyler suffered from cancer and passed away on February 18, 1994. He was survived by his brother, Keith I. Tyler; his daughters, Helen Parisi and Ann Fathy; and his son, Ralph W. Tyler, Jr.
Some of his more famous projects included: Director of Evaluation, Eight-Year Study (1934-42); Director, Cooperative Study in General Education (1939-45); Director, Examinations Staff, U.S. Armed Forces Institute (1943-53); Chairman, Exploratory Committee on Assessing the Progress of Education (1964-68); and Senior Consultant, Science Research Associates, Inc. (1967-82).
He was also a member of a number of associations and throughout the course of his career held broad associations well beyond the University of Chicago including: Member, National Advisory Mental Health Council (1959-63); Chairman, National Commission on Resources for Youth (1964-79); Chairman, National Commission for Cooperative Education (1962-75); Honorary Life Chairman (1975-?); President, National Academy of Education (1965-69); Chairman, Research Advisory Council of the U.S. Office of Education (1967-70); Member, National Science Board, 1962-68; Vice Chairman (1966-68); and Member, National Advisory Council on the Education of Disadvantaged Children (1965-72)
Some of his notable publications were: Constructing Achievement Tests (1934); Appraising and Recording Student Progress, with E.R. Smith (1942); Basic Principles of Curriculum and Instruction (1949); Educational Evaluation; New Roles, New Means, editor (1969); Crucial Issues in Testing, with R. Wolf (1974); Perspectives on American Education (1976); "Changing Concepts of Educational Evaluation." [Monograph] International Journal of Educational Research 10 (1986).
Scope Note
Tyler papers contain correspondence, minutes, sample dissertations, examinations, manuscripts of speeches and articles, published works, biographical material, and letters of recommendation. Papers document Tyler's involvement with the United States Department of Agriculture Extension Service workshops, Doane College, the American Council on Education, and the University of Chicago Department of Education and Division of Social Sciences, as well as other organizations.
The Ralph W. Tyler Papers have been arranged into eight series: I. University of Chicago, II. Biographical and Personal Papers, III. Correspondence, IV. Writings by Tyler, V. Writings by Others, VI. Audio-Visual, VII. Restricted, and VIII. Oversized.
SERIES I – UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO - DEAN, DEPARTMENT, AND DIVISION
Includes material from the period 1945-1949, reflecting some of Tyler's activities as Department Education Chair, as acting Dean of the Division of Social Sciences (1946-1948), and as Dean of the Division of Social Sciences (1948-1953). The majority of the papers in Series I concern Tyler’s administrative work, and therefore the bulk of the series is made up of correspondence and reports arranged in alphabetical order by topic/subject, or occasionally by author.
SERIES II – BIOGRAPHICAL AND PERSONAL PAPERS
Consists of standard biographical information and personal materials including awards, honorary degrees, resumes, as well as a number of dissertations written about Tyler.
SERIES III – CORRESPONDENCE
The correspondence in this series is of an academic and professional nature. It has been arranged into chronological subseries of 1942-1945, 1946-1982, and 1981-1988. Within each group the folders are alphabetized by subject matter or respondent. The majority of correspondence that Tyler engaged in during the 1981-1988 time period was via his involvement with the System Development Foundation. Within the last subseries of the correspondence, 1981-1988, there is a variety of exchanges between Tyler and Mortimer Adler that are arranged according to topic, including the Institute for Philosophical Research and the Paideia Proposal.
SERIES IV - WRITINGS BY TYLER
This series includes reprints, copies, original manuscripts and drafts by Tyler and has been organized into eleven subseries: (1) Bibliography; (2) Periodicals; (3) Books, Pamphlets, & Papers; (4) Theses; (5) Reprinted Materials; (6) Reprints and Drafts; (7) Speeches and Writings; (8) Center for Advanced Study of Behavior Sciences; (9) Publications; (10) Academic & Professional Material; and (11) Speeches 1982-1983.
SERIES V - WRITINGS BY OTHERS
This series includes writings pertaining to Tyler, however many are articles he collected or were sent to him regarding education. It has been organized into three subseries: (1) Reports, (2) Articles and Manuscripts, and (3) Dissertations.
SERIES VI - AUDIO-VISUAL
This series includes audio tapes (reel-to-reel tapes and cassettes) and video tapes, most of which are of Tyler speaking. He is known to have produced several.
SERIES VII - RESTRICTED
The majority of the restricted material is employment recommendations or student grades or recommendations. This material is not open until 2068.
SERIES VIII -- OVERSIZED
This series contains oversized material relating to Tyler's research and writing.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Tyler, Ralph Winfred, 1902-; United States. Extension Service; American Council on Education; Doane College; University of Chicago. Dept. of Education; University of Chicago. Division of the Social Sciences; Teachers -- Training of; Education
INVENTORY
- Series I: University of Chicago - Dean, Department, & Division
  - ABC Company-Administrator (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agriculture and Rural Life; Faculty Exploratory Group at the University of Chicago (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aikin-American Association for Adult Education (including Army civilian education programs) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Association of School Administrators-American Book Co. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Council on Education; Bulletins (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Council on Education; Cooperative Study in General Education (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Council on Education; Cooperative Test Service, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education; Cooperative Test Service, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education; Cooperative Test Service, 1945-6 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education; Cooperative Test Service, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education; Editor of Publications, 1946-7 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education; Executive Committee Minutes, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education; Executive Committee Minutes, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education; Measurement and Guidance, Committee, 1946-7 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education; Measurement and Guidance, Committee (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - American Council on Education; Pharmaceutical Survey (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Council on Education; Problems and Policies Committee, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education; Problems and Policies Committee, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education; Problems and Policies Committee, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education; Relationships of Higher Education to the Federal Government, Committee, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education; Relationships of Higher Education to the Federal Government, Committee, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education; Relationships of Higher Education to the Federal Government, Committee, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, correspondence (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, unidentified photograph (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, "K. W. Bigelows Ms.", Introduction and chapters I to IV (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, "KVB, Final Report (2)", Chapter I The Commission and Its Program Chapter II Basic General Ideas Chapter III Cooperative Techniques (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, "KVB, Final Report (2)", Chapter IV Ways of Working Locally Chapter V Conclusions Regarding Factors in Teacher Education Chapter VII Conclusions Regarding the Growth of Teachers I Service (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, Division of Child Development and Teacher Personnel "The Socialization of the Individual" (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, "Physiological Aspects of Child Growth and Development" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, "Child Development and the Psychology of Learning" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, "Aspects of Child Growth and Development" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, center of documentation at the University of Chicago; Bibliographical materials (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, center of documentation at the University of Chicago; Bibliographical materials (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, center of documentation at the University of Chicago; Bibliographical materials (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, center of documentation at the University of Chicago; Bibliographical materials (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Commission on, Dan Frescott, Helping Teachers Understand Children, correspondence and Chapters I-III (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Chapters IV-V (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Chapter VI-VII (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Council on Education; Teacher Education, Chapter VIII (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - American Dental Association (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Home Economics Association (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - American Psychological Association (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - American Public Health Association (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - American Red Cross (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Anderson, Harry (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Anderson-Atkinson (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Atomic weapons conference at the University of Chicago, December 12-15, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Audio-Visual Center, University of Chicago (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Axline, Virginia (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Bachrach-Benjamin (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Benson-Berkeley (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Bettelheim-Bloom (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Board of Examinations, University of Chicago (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Boardman-Buelke (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Buildings and Grounds, University of Chicago (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Burns-Byerly (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Caldwell, Otis (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - California, Community Health Education Project (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cameron-Carver (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Central Administration, University of Chicago (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chadderdon-Chase (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chicago City College (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chicago City Public Schools (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chicago Home for Girls (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Motor Club (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Chicago Schools Journal - Clark, Jane (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Classical Association of the Middle West and South (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Cleveland Conferences 1946-7, Education and the International Scene (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Close, Kenneth - College Promotion Committee (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C; 1941-1944 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C; Study of Educational Progress;1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-January 1945-July 1945 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-August 1945-June 1946 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-August 1946-October 1946 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-November 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-Health Education Program (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - College Evaluation Study, B of C-miscellaneous and undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cook-Cooper (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Cooperative Organization of Colleges and Universities, Part I (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Cooperative Organization of Colleges and Universities, Part II (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Corey-Corley (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Counseling Center, University of Chicago (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Course Outline; Education 396, on principles of test construction (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Cozine-Cronbach (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Curriculum Development, Conference on, University of Chicago Department of Education, October 1947 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dain-Davis (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Deans of Education of the Big Ten Universities, meeting of November 2, 3, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - DeBower-Dillon (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Dissertations in Department of Education; list and abstracts, A-F (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Dissertations in Department of Education; abstracts, G-H (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Dissertations in Department of Education; abstracts, J-L (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Dissertations in Department of Education; abstracts, M (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Dissertations in Department of Education; abstracts, P-R (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Doane College, January-May 1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Doane College, June-December 1945 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Doane College, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Doane College, January-May 1947 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Doane College, June-December 1947 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Dore-Dryden (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Dummer-Dyer (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Eby, Kermit (Congress of Industrial Organizations - CIO) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Edmiston - Education Forum (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Education Publications, Department of Education, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Education Publications, Department of Education, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Education Publications, Department of Education, 1948-9 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Educational Testing Service-Ewing (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Examinations, General (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Examinations, Masters and Doctors in Department of Education (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Examinations, Courses in Department of Education (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Examinations, Courses in Department of Education (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Committees, Department of Education (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, Department of Education (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, Department of Education, 1935-36 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1936-37 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1937-38 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1938-39 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1939-40 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1940-41 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1941-42 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1942-43 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Program Recommendations, 1946-47, 1949-50 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Report of Outside Bearings, Department of Education (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Fahs-Fawcett (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Ferguson-Fleming (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Foram-Furst (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Gall-Geisel (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - General Education Board (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - General Education Board Study of Cultural Factors in Intelligence; Tests (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Gentry-Gould (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Grace-Gray (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Great Books Course (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Grene-Guild (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Hagenson-Halstead (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Hamilton-Harrison (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Hauser-Hazen Conference (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Health, Illinois State Committee on (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Hearn-Hill (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Hobson-Horn (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Houle-Hughes (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Human Development, University of Chicago Committee on (formerly Committee on Child Development), general (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Human Development, minutes of meetings (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Human Development, minutes of Executive Committee (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Human Development, minutes of Executive Committee (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Human Development, subcommittee and seminar on research (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Human Development, subcommittee and seminar on research (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Human Development, subcommittee and seminar on research (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Human Development, research proposals (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Human Development, Child Development Club (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Humphreys-Huth (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Illinois Association - Illinois State (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Illinois Statewide High School Testing Program (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Illinois University, Radio Programs (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Indian Schools Research, University of Chicago (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Indiana - Various Institutes (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Instructional Materials Center, University of Chicago (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Instructional Materials Center, University of Chicago (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Instructional Materials Center, University of Chicago (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - International Harvester Research Project (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Irving-Iverson (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Jablonower-Josephson (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Judd Memorial Conference (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Judd-Junior (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Kansas-Korvin (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, advisory committee (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Conference for Directors and Deans of University Programs I Nursing Education (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, correspondence and miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, "A Review of the Health Education Program of the W. Kellogg Foundation", by C. E. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Consultant Services (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Pre-school planning conference (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Library field project (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Library facilities for Michigan teachers (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Coldwater Workshop, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - W. W. Kellogg Foundation, Michigan Community Health Area, Coldwater Workshop, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 15)